Guide to the Thomas Lyson Papers,1980-2007.
Lyson, Thomas A. Papers,1980-2007.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Thomas Lyson Papers, 1980-2007.
21-33-3600
Thomas A. Lyson
5.4 cubic feet.
Publications, Research Materials, Correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, course material, and publications concerning Lyson's work.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Development Sociology, Cornell University from 1987-2007.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, course material, photographs, and publications concerning Lyson's work on community, civic engagement and problem-solving approaches to development, as well as local and global aspects of agriculture, food, nutrition, and health. Papers and examinations from his years as a doctoral student at Michigan State and files and a manuscript relating to academic job searches in the late 1970s.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lyson, Thomas A.; Cornell University--Faculty.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences.Dept. of Development Sociology.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Social Aspects--United States.; Agriculture--Economic Aspects--United States.; Farms--United States.; Rural Development--United States.; Land use, Rural--United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Publications
  - Black Farming Shift-Share, 1966-80 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A.G. Labor Market/Situs, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sexrole Attitudes w/s. Brown (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NLS Migration, 1978-85 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - SSSP Integration, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Black Farmers-Phylon, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Plan to Become Teachers, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Profiling South Carolina's Ag. & Home Economics Students (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - High School Desegregation, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Shift-Share (AERI)/Sex Segregation in College Curriculums, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Colclough & Lyson-Southern Soc. Paper, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rural Civil Righrts and SC Poverty (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Teacher AERJ, 1982-84 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Farm Structure Bulletin, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gil and Doug, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sustainable Agriculuture/Biotech, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - North Carolina (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Farmer's Market, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - CIARE, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Big Business and Community Welfare, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Small Establishment (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Commodity-Civic, 1995-00 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - S-114 Bulletin: Sys. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - FALK-Teacher Paper, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - B-W Curric Choice, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Intra-Industry Situs (Revision of RSS), 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - SAAS-Panel Presentation, S-114 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Appaiachian Youth Paper (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Buddy Can You Spare A Job...TAS The New Academic Hustle, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Farm Youth Paper IJCS, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Fotonove 112 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Famer's Study-Burch/Lyson (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Occupational Values and Commitment to Farming (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Starr, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Curriculum Typicality-Soc. & Soc. Reserves, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sex Differences-RS, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Ag. Performance in Two Dairy Communities (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Milk, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Production Function, Crop Diversity and Conventional Vs. Sustainable Ag., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Decisions on Farms, 1983-85 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Private-Public, 1988-95 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Black Land Grant Colleges, 1983-95 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - SSSP-Unemployment, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Sex Role Status Attainment, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sex Differences-Male or Female Career Line, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Cruise Dairy, 1990-93 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - AGRIC-OCC-NZ-US, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Growing Divergence Btwn Rural and Urban South, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Some Planned to be Sociologists/SSSP-Boston, 1981-83 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - AG Studen-Farm Plan, Drafts RS, 1978-79 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Sex Role-Career Ambition w/s. Brown, SSS-Knoxville, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Factors Related to how Ag. Scientists View Advanced Biotechnologies, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Oversupply-Underutilization SSSP, 1980-83 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Nonacademic Employ, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Teacher Desideratum, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Regional Paper, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Teacher-Attitudes/Background, RSS San Franscisco, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - AG. Women/Farm Plans, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - EEOC Analysis, 1979-82 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Agricultural Service Firms, 1983-85 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Recruitment to Farming, 1981-83 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Symposium, 1983-85 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - OCC. Concentration, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Race & Minorities, 1989-90 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Longitudinal Farm Plans-NLS, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Farm Labor, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Industrial Policy & Rural America, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Stover/Lyson/Stover Paper, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Economy & Society, 1984-88 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The "Invisible Hand" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Remaking the American Food System, 2002-03 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Farming Alone, 1997-98 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Production to Development, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Harper & Lyson-"Labor Exchange Among Dairy Farmers" (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Paper-Bovine & Dairy Articles, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Community Engagement & Dairy Farm Performance, 1997-99 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sm. Manufacturing & Civic Welfare, 1994-95 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Civic AG Choices, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sustainable Ag. in American Land Grant Universities, 1996-97 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Agricultural Marketscape, 1996-98 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Publications I, 1984-87 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Publications II, 2004-05 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Central Valley Partnership, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - DCP, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Occ. Coding, 1910-30 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Transformation of NY Food and Ag. System, 1996-98 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Holy Earth & Prospectus, 1996-97 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Global Capital & Transformation of Rural Communitites, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Culture & Agriculture, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Social Capital & the Civic Comm., 2003 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Sm. Manufacturing & Nonmetropolitan Socioeconomic Well-being, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Tolbert-Earnings Inequality, 1991-92 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - NY-GA Vol.2, 1910-30 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Five Cities, 1986-90 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lost Ground in 1980's, 1990-91 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lyson-FALK Chapter in Descent (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - NZ-US Women-IICS, 1981-87 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Policy Chapter, 1989-90 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Soc. of Soc./Applied, 1987-89 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sectoral Model of Ag. Labor, IRSA, Mexico City, 1980-82 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ASR Comment, 1984-85 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rural South in Crisis (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Branch Plants & Poverty in the American South, 1983-92 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Atlanta Conference, 1987-88 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - TAS Paper, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Greg Squires, 1989-90 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Black-Sex-Role/Psych of Women Quart, 1981-82 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - SSS Panel-Social Policy (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - SAAS Teacher Paper, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Regional Context & Career Plans-Beegle Paper (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Desgregation Paper, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ag. & Farming Images from TV News, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Food and Society Conference, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "NYS Children in Poverty"/NYS Home Ec Assn. Endicott, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Crop Rotation Patterns-NY, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - NYS Farming Structure, 1986-96 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Changing Structure of South Carolina Ag. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Problems and Issues of Rural Michigan (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - RSS Food, 1995-99 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Book Materials, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Trade Rules Work Shop, 2003-04 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Local Food Project @ Airlie, 2003-04 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cornell Small Farms, 2002-04 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Babson College, 1999-06 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - PhD Shift-Share, 1977-78 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Producer Welfare Benefits from State Ag. Bargaining Laws, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Comm. Types & Social Indicator Rates, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Civic Farmers, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Qual Methods, 1998-03 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Big Business & Comm. Welfare, 1997-01 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Sheepskin are for Sheep: A Prophylaxis for Spiritual Demise" (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Dairy Farming, 1992-93 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - AAAS-rBST, 1994-95 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Publications, 1995-98 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - FAP, 1994-97 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Facing the Dairy Industry, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Book Reviews-Phoiadis/SHER, 1981-92 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Book Manuscript on Academic Job Searches, no date (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - History of Sociology Job Market, no date (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Civic Agriculture and Community Problem Solving, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Sociology Papers and Manuscripts, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence & Articles, 1990-97 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence I, 1989-06 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence II, 1976-05 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Michigan State University Correspondence (Grad. Student), 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Harry K. Schwarzweller Correspondence, 1977-1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Job Inquiry Correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Job Inquiry Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series III: Course Material
  - Rural Sociology, 1987-94 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scheduling Classes, 1976-77 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Handbook Rural Studies, 1991-2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Exams I, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Exams II, 1975-1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lecture Material, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lectures/Course Material, Spring, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lecture Material, DS-101, 1987-2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lectures, 1986-1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Course Material, RS-101 & RS 370 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, RS-101, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - RS-102 Materials, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Course Material RS-102, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - RS-102 Spring, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - RS-102 Extra Lectures, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sustainable Ag. & Dev. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Handouts RS-102, Spring, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Course Material RS-301, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - RS-301 Handouts (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - RS-301 Fall, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - RS-359/659 Fall, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - RS-359 Materials/Handouts, 1958-1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - RS-370, DGM 25, 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - RS-370/Soc-371, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - RS-370 Fall, 1992-2002 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - DS-370, 1977-2005 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - NS-380, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - RS-560, 1992-2000 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - RS-715, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Course Material, 1966-2002 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Food-Ag. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - New Ag. Lecture Notes (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Intro 241-Summer, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - RS-661 & RS-666, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - RSS Display-Finals and Orignal, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Student Papers, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Industrial Ag. and Future of Rural NY, SLide Outline (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Student Evaluations, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Class Material-Misc., 1989-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NRI, NSF, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rural Sociology, 1989-90 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Proposal-Rural Sociology, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Grants/Proposals I, 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Grants/Proposals II, 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Grants/Proposals III, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Grants/Proposals IV, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Grants/Proposals V, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Grants/Proposals VI, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Grants/Proposals VII, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Grants/Proposals VIII, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Grants/Proposals IX, 1996-2004 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous
  - Project: Organizational & Structural Changes in the Dairy Industry, 1990-1995 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NE Training & Support Network for Agricultural Development, 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Eco Village Info, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - New Zealand Dairy Industry, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - NRSC-Final Report, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Migrant, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Dairy (Regional), 1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Kiwi Fruit-Chas. Meeting, November 7th, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Plums-D, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - 1900 Census, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Integrative Graduate Education & Research Traineeship, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Potato Growers Study, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - New Zealand, 1984-1993 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Dairy, 1980-1997 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Bangkok, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Survey-Apple Growers, NYS & Michigan, 2002-03 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - FISH, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous, 1985-02 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lyson Academic Personel Evaluation - Clemson U., 1977-1982 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Lyson's Comprehensive Exam, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Michigan State work, no date (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dissertation Proposal: Reginal Context, Structural Determinants and Social Inequalities in the Educational Tracking of Rural Youth, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous West Virgina University Class Work, 1968-1975 (Box 6, Folder 13)